all right
[Music]
arithmetology sugar alcohol naturally
found in small quantities in certain
fruits and vegetables now produced in
mass quantities commercially for use as
a sweetener that's about 70 of Swedish
table sugar previously it talked about
its role in actively preventing tooth
decay it's reported to be totally safe
with almost no calories and as a bonus
it's less laxative
that's always a good selling point
erythritol is the highest digestive
tolerance of all the sugar alcohols but
how much is that really saying I'll talk
about the case report of the air
stewardess with puzzling diarrhea found
to be not so puzzling given how much
Sorbitol containing sugar-free gum she
was chewing sorbitol has also been
implicated in Halloween diarrhea where
people eat one too many sugar-free
candies
erythritol however is said to be well
tolerated even up to 80 grams if it's
spread out throughout the day which is
like 19 teaspoons with a sugar
equivalent of what you find in like a 20
ounce bottle of Mountain Dew in terms of
a single dose though the average weight
man in the U.S could get away with 14
teaspoons of erythritol at a time and
the average weight woman 15 teaspoons
children do not appear to be more
sensitive on a per weight basis but
basically they're so much lighter the
maximum dose would be more like three or
four teaspoons at a time since above
that you start seeing diarrhea and or
severe gastrointestinal symptoms while
adults may get away with Downing like a
quarter cup at a time that's based on
when they started having the runs if you
don't want to have any symptoms you'd
want to stick to under about three
tablespoons at a time since once you hit
four it can make you nauseated and give
you more berygmai a fancy medical term
for rumbling in your tummy
erythritol is also purported to have
antioxidant properties I did a video
about the paper that first discovered it
but that was just demonstrating it in a
test tube does it actually make a
difference
erythritol appears to have endothelial
protective effects meaning protecting
the cells that line Our arteries under
normal blood sugar conditions little
effect but stress them out in a Petri
dish with a high blood sugars and
erythritol protect its human endothelial
cells under normal blood sugars a few
endothelial cells were dying off but
under high blood sugar cell death shoots
up but add some erythritol at that same
high blood sugar level and death comes
back down
erythritol attenuates cell death induced
by diabetic stressors the researchers
conclude that erythritol may have a
therapeutically important protective
effect on endothelial cells but you
don't know
until you put it to the test effects of
erythritol on endothelial function in
patients with type 2 diabetes and
erythritol consumption acutely improved
small vessel endothelial function and
chronically reduced major artery
stiffness the researchers conclude that
the beneficial effects of erythritol may
be clinically relevant if confirmed in a
controlled study wait it wasn't
controlled no so you don't know if it
would have just happened anyway so
validation of these findings will
require a randomized placebo-controlled
study which should be easy to do since
there's lots of things you could
secretly swap in for the erythritol and
no we would know
hasn't been done yet but things were
looking pretty good for erythritol and
then
erythritol is associated with body fat
gain in young adults
what
erythritol is a predictive biomarker for
metabolic dysfunction significantly
associated with getting diabetes
significantly associated with getting
coronary heart disease what is going on
we will find out
next
[Music]
thank you